yeah
hi guys I'm Jade fault and in today's
lesson we're going to talk about
developing speed using a single bass
drum pedal
now if you are double pedal player you
can still use these exercises to develop
speed with each foot individually ok so
you can practice with your right foot
and then also practice them with your
left foot
these are some exercises i developed I'm
calling the beginning exercises but
obviously it's all about the kind of a
temple you play than that so if you want
to play them really really fast
that would obviously be more of an
advanced speed stuff like that but
Before we jump into that wanted to talk
a little bit about just the techniques
that you're using now you'll notice I'm
using what what Sean lang calls the flat
foot technique and that's where my foot
is just my the heel of the foot is
slightly off the pedal and when I
actually go fast i'm using this
technique
ok if you want you can bring your your
foot on top of the pedal
however when going fast and stuff like
that is I find if I move my foot
you know just halfway down the pedal I'm
able to get faster and it will be easier
and i'll be able to play those strokes
for longer and so that's why I'm doing
that you'll also notice I'm not using
heel down
ok I want to get a little bit more
powerful of stroke so i'm using that
heal up flat foot technique if you want
to practice with heel down there is
absolutely nothing wrong with that
I know there is a lot of heel down
drummers that that's what they play that
exclusively and that's totally fine i'm
not one to tell you what technique there
is right or what technique is wrong ok
with whatever works for you and music
you play but I'm really playing these
exercise all at two different temples
ok a slow and a fast time because i
really just want you guys to to hear how
they sound when you're first starting
out so if you're if you are beginning
you know you should play it very very
slow especially you're first starting
out but then there's always like you
always want to push it because we're
trying to develop Spieth right but speed
doesn't come with without control so we
still want to make sure we have control
and that's why we start slow and then
speed it up aggressively
so with that said let's jump in to
exercise number 1 i'm going to be
playing this at 70 beats per minute
alright so that's just a very basic
exercise to help you guys develop the
control and then you can continually
speed it up and I only max out there at
120 but obviously I would continue to
push it push it and and hopefully get to
around 180 190 200 somewhere in there
and then I'd also practice that with my
left foot especially if you want to do
some fast singles or whatever you know
you're only as fast as your slowest foot
and so it's important to work on both
feet
the next exercise we're going to do it
just incorporate some sixteenth notes in
there
ok we're going to start this at 70 beats
per minute and the group of sixteenth
notes is on count for so make sure you
guys get the sheet music for this case
you're watching this on the drum lessons
dr. website it's right below you'll find
it in that the PDF link if you're
watching someone else just go onto the
website and you'll find the sheet music
under the bass drum section
yeah
ok so what that exercise is going to
help you with is doing those short
bursts
you know where you need a quick three
strokes or a quick two strokes or
whatever it is going to help you develop
the techniques and the control to
actually play at those faster temples
the next exercise is basically to
incorporate more of those 16 notes so we
just have two eighth notes and then a
group of 16 notes 28 notes and a group
of 16 miles
ok so let's try this one at 70 beats per
minute
yeah
alright guys so getting fast with a
single pedal
there's not really any quick fix or
anything that's gonna you know
increase the speed of this within 10
minutes or stuff like that k
there are certain techniques need to
learn to do a quick doubles and stuff
like that but to play consistent and
constant notes the best and easiest way
to do it is to just practice these
exercises and started a temperature
comfortable with and then slowly
progress faster and you're going to
playing drums your whole life so don't
worry if you have to you know really
focus on bass drum technique for 12
months or 24 months or something like
that
there's absolutely nothing wrong with
that and the more control you develop
the easier it will be to go fast so I
just highly recommend start slow and
then slowly progress faster
so once you're done this beginner lesson
you can move on to the intermediate
lesson on how to build single bass drum
speed i'll see you guys there
yeah